A Finding Aid to the Irving Sandler Papers and Interviews, 1944-2017, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Irving Sandler interviews and papers
1944-2017
Archives of American Art
Sandler, Irving, 1925-
AAA.sandirvi
Archival Resource Key
2.8 Linear feet
1.63 Gigabytes
The interviews and papers of art critic, art historian, and educator Irving Sandler measure 2.8 linear feet and 1.63 GB and date from 1944-2017. Included are interviews and recorded lectures, some in digital format; photographs of artwork and artists; membership files, meeting minutes, and ephemera from the Club organization; printed material from individual artist and group exhibits; and teaching files.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as 4 series.
Series 1: Interviews, 1962-2017 (2.4 linear feet; Boxes 1-3, 1.63 GB; ER01-ER03)
Series 2: Photographs, 1955-1965 (2 folders; Box 4)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1944-1978 (7 folders; Box 4)
Series 4: Professional Activities, 1951-1969 (4 folders; Box 4)
Biographical / Historical
Irving Sandler (1925-2018) was an art critic, art historian, and educator in New York, NY. Sandler was the art critic for Art News, 1956-1962; for the New York Post, 1960-1965; and an instructor of art history at New York University, 1960-1971. During his career, he was director of the Tanager Gallery and the Club organization.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the collection was donated in 1981-1982 by Irving Sandler. Sandler donated an additional interview with Mira Lehr in 2008. Sandler's widow, Lucy Freeman Sandler, donated the 2017 interview of Charles Simonds in 2019.
Scope and Contents
The interviews and papers of Irving Sandler measure 2.8 linear feet and 1.63 GB and date from 1944-2017. Included are interviews and recorded lectures, some in digital format; photographs of artwork and artists; membership files, meeting minutes, and ephemera from the Club organization; printed material from individual artist and group exhibits; and teaching files.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research. Archival audiovisual recordings must be digitized for research access. Researchers may access digitized audiovisual materials in the Archives' Washington, D.C. or New York, N.Y. Research Centers by appointment.
Existence and Location of Copies
Some of the sound recordings in this collection have been digitized for research access and are available in the Archives of American Art offices.
Art teachers -- New York (State); Art historians -- New York (State) -- New York; Sound recordings; Interviews; Club (New York, N.Y.)
- Interviews, 1962-2017; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 2.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-3; 1.63 Gigabytes ER01-ER03
  Scope and Contents
  Interviews with various artists conducted by Irving Sandler, his students, and other persons. Name of interview is included in the folder title when known.
  - Stephen Antonakis, conducted by Martha Diamond, 1982 March 18; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Ida Applebroog, conducted by Robin Cembalest, 1982 March 18; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Item 2)
  - Elise Asher, conducted by Mary Hu and Robert Lazarus, 1982 March 21; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Item 2a)
  - Alice Baber, conducted by Claudia H. Allen, circa 1982; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 3)
  - Richard Barringer, conducted by Stuart Burlm, circa 1970-1980; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 4)
  - Nell Blaine, 1969 April 5; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 5)
  - Ilya Bolotowsky, conducted by Adelaide Freer (1967), Interview Transcript, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Item 6)
  - Ilya Bolotowsky, conducted by Adelaide Freer (1967), Digital Audio Recording, 2014; Archival Resource Key; 0.767 Gigabytes Two computer files (Folder ER01)
  - Bouchard, conducted by Irving Sandler, undated; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 7)
  - Earnest Briggs, conducted by Sister Mary Ann Petry, 1968 November 6; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 8)
  - George Campbell, conducted by Mira Berensteily, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Item 9)
  - Brad Davis, conducted by Ted Trussell Portor, 1982 April 27; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Item 10)
  - Sherman Drexler and Jack Kroll, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1962 November 12; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 11)
  - Lois Dodd, 1982 April 28; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Item 12)
  - John Ferren, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1963 February 4; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 13)
    File also includes one audio cassette tape.
  - Perle Fine, conducted by Irving Sandler; Pierre Caille, 1963 April 8; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 14)
    Includes transcript for Perle Fine interview
  - John Fischer, circa 1970-1980; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Item 15)
  - Miles Forst, 1969 March 20; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 16)
  - Michael Goldberg, conducted by Lynne Miller, 1969 April 23; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 17)
    Includes transcript
  - Leon Golub, conducted by Irving Sandler, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 18)
  - Adolph Gottlieb, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1962 October 10; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Item 19)
  - Stanley W. Hayter, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1962 December 10; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Item 20)
  - Carl Holty, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1967 September 5; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 1)
  - Carl Holty and Harry Holtzman, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1962 March 26; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel; 1 Sound cassette (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Alfred Jensen, conducted by Irving Sandler and Michael Torlen, 1975 May 15; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 2, Item 3)
  - Wolf Kahn, conducted by Irving Sandler and his class, 1969; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 4)
  - Aristodimos Kaldis, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1968 November 21; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 5)
  - Howard Kanovitz, conducted by Arthur Post, circa 1982; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Item 6)
  - Ivan C. Karp, conducted by Sarah Bankson, 1982 April 22; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 2, Item 7)
  - Lila Katzen, conducted by Deena Lahn, 1982 March 10; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 2, Item 8)
  - Robert Kaupelis, conducted by Thomas Cort Rubin, 1982; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Item 9)
  - Lyman Kipp, 1968; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 10)
  - Mira Lehr, conducted by Irving Sandler, Digital Audio Recording, 2007 December 6-7; Archival Resource Key; 0.032 Gigabytes Two computer files (Folder ER02)
  - Marcia Marcus, conducted by Jill Magen, 1982 April 17; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Item 12)
  - George McNeil talk at New York University, 1968 November 26; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 13)
  - Kyle Morris, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1969 April 24; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 14)
  - Man Ray, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1963 April 1; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels; 1 Sound cassette (Box 2, Item 15)
    Includes Transcript
  - Corinne Robins, conducted by Holly Hughes, 1982 March 16; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 2, Item 16)
  - Salvatore Romano, conducted by Manuel J. Borja, undated; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Item 17)
  - Edwin Ruda, conducted by William S. O'Brien, 1968 April 3; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 18)
  - Maurice Sievan, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1963 January 14; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 19)
  - Charles Simonds, conducted by Irving Sandler, Digital Audio Recording and Documents, July 31, 2017; Archival Resource Key; 0.836 Gigabytes Nine computer files (Folder ER03)
  - Joseph Solomon, conducted by Irving Sandler, undated; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 21)
  - Jack Sonenberg, 1982 March 19; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 2, Item 22)
  - Nancy Spero, conducted by Judith Rodenbeck, 1982 May 9; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Richard Stankiewicz, conducted by Irving Sandler, 1979 May 3; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 2)
  - Joe Stefanelli, conducted by Rhonda K. Garelick, 1982 April; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 3)
  - May Stevens, conducted by Mary Charlotte Domandi, 1982 March 19; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Tony Underhill, 1968 March; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 3, Item 5)
  - Estaban Vicente, conducted by Vicente Todoli, 1982 April 12; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 6)
  - Idelle Weber, conducted by Christopher Kandel, 1982 March 8; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 7)
- Photographs, 1955-1965; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 4
  Primarily composed of images of artwork. There is also a photograph of Robert Rauschenberg, circa 1955-1965.
  - Photographs of works of art, 1955-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Robert Rauschenberg, Photograph, circa 1955-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Printed Material, 1944-1978; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 7 Folders Box 4
  This series includes artist and group exhibition flyers, programs, and invitations.
  - John Chamberlain, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Adja Yunkers, 1957-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Artists, 1950-1969, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5-8)
  - Groups, 1944-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Professional Activities, 1951-1969; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 4
  Meeting minutes, membership files, and ephemera related to Sandler's involvement with the Club organization; teaching files; and the transcript of a panel discussion titled, "The Content of Abstract Art," which Sandler moderated.
  - The Club, meeting minutes and membership lists, 1952-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The Club, papers, 1951-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Irving Sandler, Moderator, "The Content of Abstract Art", circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Student Papers, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)